A Guide to the Richard Lee Bland Collection of Richmond Memorabilia, 1880s-1990s
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Richard Lee Bland Collection of Richmond Memorabilia, 1880s-1990s
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 32
2 linear feet plus architectural drawings
Richard Lee Bland
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was deposited to Special Collections and Archives by Richard Bland in September, 1995.
Biographical/Historical Information
Richmond artist Richard Lee Bland (1950-) has been active in the Richmond art scene since 1968 after his admission into the School of the Arts, Richmond Professional Institute (now VCU). Bland describes himself as an impressionist painter. His vision for art developed from performance and conceptual art in tangent with "a compelling belief in impressionistic painting." Bland's mentor, Eliot Clark (1883-1980), an American Impressionist, was the last surviving participant of the Cos Cob Art Colony (1890-1900).
Bland is critical of commercial art galleries, co-operative groups, and university art education practices. "I believe the artist must maintain an aesthetic apart from institutional curriculum," Bland said in 1995. "Self-reliance and community involvement help the artist confront relevant issues in a spirited fine art."
Bland has had numerous art exhibits and is well known within the arts community in Richmond. He produced an experimental non-commercial alternative space, The Grove Avenue Gallery (1982-1984), to promote what he called a "bedrock" for independent Richmond art culture. He left for New York City in 1984 to practice art then returned to Richmond in 1986. He then purchased an old dairy barn in the lower Fan District converting it to a studio residence. Bland has established a growing archive of Richmond material, including vintage photographs, architectural drawings of historic Richmond buildings, and other artifacts of the city, that he calls a "a personal resource" of artistic inspiration.
Scope and Content Information
Collection consists of a variety of Richmond, Virginia related materials that Bland has gathered since the 1970s. The collection includes three original architectural drawings of Richmond's Cathedral of the Sacred Heart; drawings of plans and photographs of what was to become the power house of the Virginia Railway and Power Co. on Richmond's 12th Street and numerous other early 20th century drawings and materials documenting electrical plans for the city.
The collection also contains material documenting the arts in Richmond from the 1890s to the present, including material on the various art organizations that have existed in the city; rock music of the 1980s; and correspondence and other material regarding Bland's Grove Avenue Gallery (1982-1984). Other materials related to the history of Richmond include late 19th and early 20th business invoices and correspondence; streetcar ephemera of the 1940s; and numerous published materials and a wide assortment of ephemera items and photographs relating to wide cross section of Richmond's cultural history.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Collection is arranged by series and alphabetically therein.
Organization
The items in Folders 1-8, Map Case #11, were found by Bland at an abandoned building in the 1980s. The building may have been the former site of the R.R. Cosby Electrical Co. which had operated in Richmond, Virginia for almost the entire 20th century. Other items, located in Boxes 1-6 and in Folder 9-10, Map Case #11, have been acquired by Bland at flea markets, garage sales, through dealers and at other locations.
The collection is divided into the following series:
Series I--Art, Artists, & Craftsmen (1890s-1990s)
Series II--General (1880s-1980s)
Series III--Grove Avenue Gallery (1982-1984)
Series IV--Ledger from Maxwell & McGowan and McGowan and Pearsall House Furnishers (1901-1902)
Series V--Richmond Art Glass (late 19th/early 20th century)
Series VI-- Historic Richmond (late 19th/early 20th century)
Series VII--Architectural Drawings and Oversize materials (1880s-1980s)
Contents List
- Series I--Art, Artists, and Craftsmen 1890s-1990s
  - Academy of Arts and Sciences, n.d. 1935-1937 (Box 1)
  - Academy of Sciences and Fine Arts 1938 (Box 1)
  - Anderson, George W. and Sons, Carpets and Oil Cloths 1899 (Box 1)
  - Chester A. Arthur, Richmond Painter-Application for membership into the Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paper Hangers 1911 (Box 1)
  - Chester A. Arthur, Richmond Painter-Old Dominion Steamship Co. Receipt 1917 (Box 1)
  - Chester A. Arthur, Richmond Painter-Bemis Brothers Bag Co. Notice 1917 (Box 1)
  - Chester A. Arthur, Richmond Painter-Standard Time Exchange Notice 1933 (Box 1)
  - Chester A. Arthur, Richmond Painter-F.W. Devoe and C.T. Reynolds Co. of New York Receipt 1916 (Box 1)
  - Chester A. Arthur, Richmond Painter-Oscar Schlegel Mfg. Co., Sign Painters Receipt 1917 (Box 1)
  - Art Club: Constitution and By-Laws 1897 (Box 1)
  - Art Society of Richmond 1895 (Box 1)
  - Art Society of Richmond 1991 (Box 1)
  - Artspace Gallery, n.d. 1995 (Box 1)
  - Beaux-Arts Ball, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Blaine, Nell-Artist, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Bland, Richard, History of Art Organizations in Richmond, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Bruce, Patrick Henry- Place in the Arts is Sought for Modernist Bruce By Roberts (Box 1)
  - Camera Club of Richmond, Virginia 1935 (Box 1)
  - Coffey, Roger L., n.d. (Box 1)
  - Grove Avenue Gallery (miscellaneous papers), n.d. 1893-1984 (Box 1)
    (See also box 5)
  - Fulton Brick Works December 16, 1924 (Box 2)
  - Henry Street Gallery in first exhibit Friday, The Richmond News Leader November 29, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Johnston, George Benjamin M.D., Photographs 1895, 1905 (Box 2)
  - List of Exhibits 1975-1980 (Box 2)
  - Lord Fairfax Waffle Shop, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1869-1963 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Artists 1938-1958 (Box 2)
  - Norfolk College Art Department 1898 (Box 2)
  - Photographers-Homeier and Clark, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Photographers-H.P. Cook, n.d. 1915 (Box 2)
  - Photographers-Thomas Christian 1902-1903 (Box 2)
  - Pinkham Ryder, Albert Introductory Critique 1942 (Box 2)
  - Poems, Two Books (one by James Brunot, the other by Rik Davis), n.d. (Box 2)
  - Poetic Richmond(Cover by Bland) 1982 (Box 2)
  - Richmond Art Club 1898-1914 (Box 2)
  - Richmond Art Co.-The Antique Galleries, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Spectrum (March, May) 1969 (Box 2)
  - Tournament of Arts and Crafts (including a price list), n.d. 1931 (Box 2)
  - USA Today(Life Section); including Pop Art's Peter Pan(Andy Warhol) February 23, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Tray-Boy School of Dance 1926-1927 (Box 2)
  - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, n.d. 1937-1939 (Box 2)
  - Walker, Douglas Stewart-Artist, n.d. (Box 2)
  - West, Albert, Architect 1895 (Box 2)
- Series II--General 1880s-1980s
  - Aeroplane: Acrobatics and Thrill Rides(poster) July 25, 1920 (Box 3)
  - Allen and Ginter, Purchase Order Forms 1889 (Box 3)
  - Asia Company, Oriental Gifts Shop, 2 North Belmont Ave. (Box 3)
  - Barnes, T.N. Grocer 1911 (Box 3)
  - Black Panthers 1969 (Box 3)
  - Bland, Richard L.: Transcript and Student Fees 1968 (Box 3)
  - Berry-Burk and Co., Men's Store 1950s (Box 3)
  - Cavalier Magazine 1930 (Box 3)
  - Century Magazine, and article on Jefferson's House 1887 (Box 3)
  - Chesapeake and Potomac Telephone Co., Va (Box 3)
  - Cigarette and Cigar Papers (miscellaneous), n.d. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence (miscellaneous) 1919-1949 (Box 3)
  - E.P. Murphy and Son 1909 (Box 3)
  - Etc.: A Review of General Semantics-A Journal Devoted to the Role of Symbols in Human Behavior 1987 (Box 3)
  - Forest Garden Theater, Fall 1922 (Box 3)
  - The Glenette, Glen Allen Elementary School Annual 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Green Devils, RPI Folder (Box 3)
  - Greenwood M.E. Church, Longdale Virginia (Box 3)
  - Happy Hour, Barguide (Box 3)
  - Map of Historical Tidewater Ned. (Box 3)
  - Map of Korea, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Medical Students working on cadaver, photograph (Box 3)
  - Meyer Greentree Clothing 1938 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, Newspaper Clippings 1894-1982 (Box 3)
  - Monticello Brochure and Ticket, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Monticello Wine Co. 1910 (Box 3)
  - The News Leader August 6, 1915 (Box 3)
  - Photographs (8) By the Old James River Canal (Box 3)
    Photographs of construction of what was to become the powerhouse of the Virginia Railway and Power Co. on Richmond's 12th Street. The original photographs have been re-photographed and enlarged. Dates unknown. Photographs, Inter-racial military company; a photograph of a child by M.J. Powers, Richmond, Va; photograph of 'Operetta Pickles John Marshall Highschool, Richmond, Va)
  - Pick Me Up and Lay Me Down and other Songs In Dear Old Dixie Land, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Richmond Public Schools, First Honor Certificate 1932 (Box 3)
  - Original Menu from Paul's Restaurant, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Program for Hair 1969 (Box 4)
  - Reciepts (miscellaneous Richmond businesses) 1920-1964 (Box 4)
  - Receipts (Building Materials) 1920s (Box 4)
  - Receipts (Planter's National Bank) 1920s (Box 4)
  - Reinach 1906 (Box 4)
  - Richmond, Fredricksburg and Potomac Railroad 1965 (Box 4)
  - Richmond Professional Institute-Bulletin, etc. 1959-1968 (Box 4)
  - Richmond Reverie, by Margaret Dashiell (Box 4)
  - Richmond Tour guide Map 1960s (Box 4)
  - RPI Bulletin 1963-1964 (Box 4)
  - RPI Bulletin 1968 (Box 4)
  - RPI Hawks and Sparrows/ Flash Gordon, n.d. (Box 4)
  - RPI Spectrum (Box 4)
  - RPI Student Snapshots, n.d. (Box 4)
  - RPI, Student Art Exhibition, n.d. (Box 4)
  - RPI, Students, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Richmond Department of Public Safety 1919 (Box 4)
  - Richmond Photo 1980s (Box 4)
  - Richmond Water and Gas Works 1890s-1940s (Box 4)
  - Rik Davis Poems 1940s-1983 (Box 4)
  - RVA Punk Nation, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Southern Railway Co. 1898 (Box 4)
  - Stewart Circle Pharmacy, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Tantilla Garden Richmond, Va 1948 (Box 4)
  - To the Working People of Richmond, n.d. (Box 4)
  - The Village Cafe-General Information and newspaper clippings 1980-1992 (Box 4)
  - Village Cafe Menu, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University, Introduction to the Arts 1969 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University 1969 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University, Newsletter 1969 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University, News Bulletin 1969 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University, Notice to Returning Students 1968 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University, The Galslight and Signpost 1968 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University- Rhoads Hall is Dedicated Proscript May 17, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University, Student Gov't Booklet, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University, Student Gov't Newsletter, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University, Student Probation 1969 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Electric and Power Company-Weekly Pass, Tickets advertisements 1940-1943 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Electric and Power Company 1927, 1940-2 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Railway and Power Company, Richmond, Virginia, n.d. 1894-1924 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Transit Company, Weekly Pass 1947 (Box 4)
  - University of Virginia, Admission of Women 1918 (Box 4)
  - University of Virginia, Alumni News 1932 (Box 4)
  - University of Virginia, Leave of Absence 1889 (Box 4)
  - University of Virginia Law 1892 (Box 4)
  - Watkins Nurseries, Chesterfield Co., Catalog 1940 (Box 4)
  - The Way Virginia Girls Kiss, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Western Union Telegraph Co. 1894-1899 (Box 4)
  - Westwood Supper Club, n.d. 1946 (Box 4)
  - We've got to have Money-program at MCV, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Woody, Sam, Commissioner of Revenue, n.d. (Box 4)
  - WRVA Dialog 1951 (Box 4)
- Series III--Grove Avenue Gallery 1982-1984 (Box 5)
  This box contains three scrapbooks with articles and flyers for the Grove Avenue Gallery, Richmond, Va.
- Series IV--Ledger from Maxwell and McGowan and McGowan and Pearsall House Furnishers 1901-1902 (Box 6-6a)
  This box contains a ledger from Maxwell and McGowan and McGowan and Pearsall. The ledger for these two companies dates to 1901 and 1902. The companies are listed as General House Furnisher. The company was called Maxwell and McGowan in 1901 and it apparently changed hands in 1902. The ledger has receipts of the purchases made by the two companies. The items on the receipts include; chairs, lamps, palm fans, clocks, photograph albums, etc. The companies providing these items include: Marietta Chair Co. of Marietta, Georgia; Mercer Pottery Co. of Trenton, New Jersey; Eureka Furniture and Manufacturing Co. of Manchester, Virginia; Jamestown Bedstead Co. of New York; and Hagerstown Table Works of Hagerstown, Maryland. The Richmond City Directory for 1901 includes the following entry; Maxwell & McGowan (Thos R Maxwell and Geo W McGowan), furniture 1445 e Main. The 1902 City Directory lists; McGowan and Pearsall (Geo W McGowan and E Frank Pearsall) furniture 1445 e Main.
- Series V--Richmond Art Glass
  - Behold--I stand at the Door and Knock Color Copy, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Binswanger Glass Co. Invoice, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Christ and Apostles, Original Drawing of window, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Gothic Window, Color copy, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Stagg, Thomas, Manufacturer of Paints and Glass 1897 (Box 7)
  - Unidentified Stained Glass Window, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Binswanger Window with Crown and Challis, Original Drawing (Box 7-A)
  - Christ the Shepherd Art Glass Window, Chimtaco Co., Orignal Drawing (Box 7-A)
- Series VI--Historic Richmond
  - Canal District Photographs (Box 8)
  - Canal District Reprints (Box 8)
  - Capitol Square, Photograph 1900s (Box 8)
  - Country Club of Virginia 1939 (Box 8)
  - Glen Allen Baptist Church, Constitution and By-Laws (Box 8)
  - Glen Allen Baptist Church, Member Card (Box 8)
  - Female Seminary Schools 1890s (Box 8)
  - First Church of Christ Scientist 1928 (Box 8)
  - Jefferson Hotel Sticker, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Lee Theater, Opening Night Program 1935 (Box 8)
  - Libbie Hill Park, Photo, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Map of Woodland Heights 1909 (Box 8)
  - Maymont, Interior and exterior, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Miller and Rhoads Slide (Box 8)
  - Mocha Temple, Broad Street (Box 8)
  - Monument Avenue Sculptures, ca. 1900 (Box 8)
  - Mosque Letterhead, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Mosque Theater, Patron Letter 1941 (Box 8)
  - Mosque Theater, Passion Play Leaflet (Box 8)
  - Mosque Theater, Divisions of the Department of Finance 1941 (Box 8)
  - Richmond Female Institute 1885-1886 (Box 8)
  - Richmond Howitzer's Monument 1960s (Box 8)
  - Richmond Postcards (Box 8)
  - R.E. Lee Camp Memorial 1928 (Box 8)
  - Richmond Penitentiary 1904 (Box 8)
  - St. Luke's Hospital Brochure, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Stained Glass Cartoon, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Unknown Richmond Buildings, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Virginia House, Pamphlet 1929 (Box 8)
  - Virginia Postcards, Clover Fields, Keswick; Henry Clay Birth Place, Ashland (Box 8)
- Series VII-Architectural Drawings and Oversize materials 1880s-1980s
  - Architectural Drawing May 24, 1910 (Map-case 11.1)
    Architectural Drawing of Private Garage, Mr. W. O. Randlett, Washington Ward, Richmond, Va.
  - Architectural Drawings (Map-case 11.2)
    Architectural Drawings (four), Foundation Plan, First Floor Plan, Second Floor Plan and Side Elevation of Unidentified House, n.d.
  - Architectural Drawing of Unidentified Building, Front Elevation, n.d. (Map-case 11.3)
  - Architectural Drawings 1910 (Map-case 11.4)
    Architectural Drawings (two) of Front Elevation and Side Elevation-Residence for R. C. Beverley, Ginter Park, Virginia Albert F. Huntt
  - Architectural Drawing June 16, 1902 (Map-case 11.5)
    Architectural Drawing of Probolic Roof Truss for Henry Warden, Fredericksburg, Virginia, Designed by R. Shirreff E., Richmond, Virginia
  - Imaged of proposed Jefferson Davis Monument, Monroe Park June 30, 1896 (Map-case 11.6)
    Photograph of drawing of the proposed Jefferson Davis Monument - view differs from the photograph above. Reproduced photo taken from the Richmond Dispatch, June 30, 1896. Negative #670.
  - Crossing-Transmission Line over A.C.L. Tracks October 27, 1918 (Map-case 11.7)
    Virginia Railway and Power Company near Centralia, Virginia. October 27, 1918, Milliken Patent Galvanized Steel Towers
  - Map of Proposed Transmission Line 1910 (Map-case 11.7)
    Virginia Rail and Power Co., Chester, Virginia-W.W. Laprade, May 1910, Retraced and Revised, June 1910
  - Sub Power Station and Trouble Wagon House March 5, 1910 (Map-case 11.7)
    Virginia Railway and Power Co., Harrison and Clay St., E.W.
  - Map of the James River Showing Islands February 19, 1909 (Map-case 11.8)
  - Map of the Town of Highland Park, n.d. (Map-case 11.8)
  - Map of Virginia 1932 (Map-case 11.8)
    Index to Topographic Maps and Geologic Foliers, Dept. of Interior, U.S. Geologic Survey
  - Drawing Exercise (Map-case 11.9)
  - Drawing of Passenger Engine April 27, 1890 (Map-case 11.9)
    Virginia Mechanics Institute, April 27, 1890. On reverse of drawing is written R.R. Cosby
  - Lettering Exercise No. 20 Put on all dimensions and notes as shown in Fig. 41: Reinharts F. H. Lettering (Map-case 11.9)
  - Lettering Exercise, Put on all dimensions, arrowheads and notes. Also a title containing the following. Halfside elevation of swing bridge; the Virginia Polytechnic Institute Drawing Department, n.d. (Map-case 11.9)
  - Section of Dam at Upper End of Canal-Appomattox River, Virginia Passenger and Power Company September 27, 1902 (Map-case 11.10)
  - Map of Portion of Washington Ward-Showing SRR Tracks, Traced by R.R. Cosby 5-25-1910 (Map-case 11.10)
  - Architectural Drawing March 22, 1889 (Map-case 11.10)
    Virginia Electrical Rwy. and Develop Co. - Diagram of Possible Water Power at Haxall-Crenshaw Property, March 22, 1889
  - Original Newspapers June 30, 1896 (Map-case 11.11)
    Times, Richmond, Virginia and Richmond Dispatch, June 30, 1896. These newspapers were found in the bottom of box containing other items. The box was purchased by Bland at a Flea Market and are not part of the collection of materials found by Bland at the former site of the R.R. Cosby Electrical Company.
  - Architectural Drawing, n.d. (Map-case 11.12)
    Richmond Cathedral of the Sacred Heart, Electrical Plans, Longitudinal Section
  - Architectural Drawing, n.d. (Map-case 11.12)
    Richmond Cathedral of the Sacred Heart, Electrical Plans, Main Floor Plan
  - Architectural, n.d. (Map-case 11.12)
    Richmond Cathedral of the Sacred Heart, Electrical Plans, Basement Floor Plan
  - Posters and Flyers advertising Richmond rock bands and artists 1980s (Map-case 11.13)
  - Map of Broad Street 1907 (Map-case 11.14)
    Showing Slope of Hill, Richmond Traction Company, Wm. Northrop and H. T. Wickham, Receivers, [The next line of type had the following which was scratched out: Virginia Passenger & Power Company], Profile, Broad Street between 10th and 24th Streets, Richmond. 1907, Traced by G.W. James.
  - Proposed Application of New Horizontal for Operating Pumping Machinery (Map-case 11.14)
  - Seaboard Air Line Railway Co. March 26, 1909 (Map-case 11.14)
    Bridge on Broad Street showing location of Richmond Passenger and Power Company's Conduit Line March 26, 1909
  - Map of Certain Grants located in the James River 1783-1795 1908 (Map-case 11.14)
  - Chesapeake and Ohio Railway 1908 (Map-case 11.14)
    Condensed Profile, shows Railway stops
  - Rand McNally Map of Virginia, n.d. (Map-case 11.15)